瓦雷利亚末日
伊耿一世（AC1-37 在位）
“征服者”
镶嵌红宝石的瓦雷利亚钢王冠
坦格利安家族征服维斯特洛
雷妮丝
伊耿一世的妹妹和妻子
伊尼斯一世（AC37-42 在位）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
杰赫里斯一世（AC48-103 在位）
“和解者”“人瑞王”
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
亚莉珊（AC36-100）
“善良王后”
杰赫里斯一世的妹妹和妻子
贝尔隆（AC57-101）
“勇敢的”“春晓王子”
杰赫里斯一世的儿子和国王之手
阿莱莎（AC60-84）
贝尔隆的妹妹和妻子
戴蒙
“浪荡王子”
贝尔隆的儿子 韦赛里斯一世的弟弟
科利斯·瓦列利安
“海蛇”“潮汛之主”
雷妮丝
“无冕女王”
韦赛里斯一世的堂姐
兰娜尔·瓦列利安（AC100- ）
科利斯和雷妮丝的女儿
奥托·海塔尔
韦赛里斯一世的国王之手
韦赛里斯一世（AC103开始在位至今）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
阿莉森·海塔尔
奥托的女儿 韦赛里斯一世的第二任妻子
韦赛里斯一世（AC103开始在位至今）
镶嵌翡翠和珍珠的黄金王冠
爱玛·艾林（AC82-112）
韦赛里斯一世的表妹和第一任妻子
奥托·海塔尔
韦赛里斯一世的国王之手
阿莉森·海塔尔
奥托的女儿 韦赛里斯一世的第二任妻子
雷妮拉
韦赛里斯一世的女儿和王储
改编自 《血与火：坦格利安王朝史》
[美] 乔治·马丁 著
龙 王 家 族
第一季 第五集
照亮前程 We Light the Way
- 早安 雷娅夫人 - 堂兄
-Good morrow, Lady Rhea. -Cousin.
今天的猎物是什么？兔子？
What's today's quarry? Rabbit?
- 鹿 - 不错的挑战
-Deer. -Oh. Fine challenge.
需要人陪吗？
Care for some company?
我还是想自己去
I'd rather ride alone.
祝你好运咯
Good fortune to you.
丈夫
Husband.
戴蒙·坦格利安
“浪荡王子” 韦赛里斯的弟弟
什么风把你吹来谷地了？
What brings you to the Vale?
难不成你终于要来圆房了？
Or have you at last come to consummate our marriage?
即使我不愿意
The Vale's sheep might be willing,
谷地的羊或许行
even if I'm not.
毕竟我们的羊还更好看呢
Our sheep are prettier, after all.
还是说你哥哥终于受够了你在身边晃悠
Or perhaps your brother has at last had his fill of your company.
为了个小姑娘把你丢一边了
Cast you aside in favor of a little girl.
你现在要干嘛？
What will you do now?
干掉那个孩子吗？
Will you strike the child down?
还是……
Or...
我早就知道你最后一下不行
I knew you couldn't finish.
软蛋！
Craven!
韦赛里斯·坦格利安一世
国王
莱昂诺·斯壮
国王之手
谢谢
Thank you.
克里斯顿·科尔
御林铁卫 雷妮拉·坦格利安的护卫
雷妮拉·坦格利安
龙石岛公主 王储
奥托·海塔尔
等一下
A moment.
阿莉森·海塔尔
王后 奥托之女
我不想你离开
I do not wish to see you go.
这是国王的决定
Such is the King's decision.
最让我痛惜的决定
A decision I most bitterly regret.
但这是你造成的
And yet, you made it possible.
你选择了雷妮拉
You chose Rhaenyra.
她发誓她是清白的
She swore her innocence,
而我相信她
and I believed her.
是你想相信她 她父亲也是
You wanted to believe her, as did her father.
你的线人搞错了
Your informant was wrong.
也许是个无心之过 但我没想到会变成这样！
An honest mistake, perhaps, but I did not foresee this!
你应该想到的
You should have.
还不是你非要坚持让伊耿当继承人！
If you had not been so relentless in advancing Aegon as heir!
听我说 女儿
Listen to me, daughter.
国王迟早会死
The King will die.
可能是几个月后 或是几年后 至少他不会活到老
It may be months or years, but he'll not live to be an old man.
如果雷妮拉继承了王位
And if Rhaenyra succeeds him,
战争会随之而来 你明白吗？
war will follow, do you understand?
这个国家不会接受她
The realm will not accept her.
她为了确保自己的王位主张
And to secure her claim,
会除掉你的孩子们
she'll have to put your children to the sword.
她到时候别无选择
She'll have no choice.
你也知道的
You know it.
你不傻 但你选择无视事实
You're no fool, and yet you choose not to see it.
时辰将至 阿莉森
The time is coming, Alicent.
你要么让伊耿做好登基的准备
Either you prepare Aegon to rule,
要么就巴结雷妮拉 乞求她的怜悯
or you cleave to Rhaenyra and pray for her mercy.
科利斯大人在哪？他应该等在这接待国王的
Where is Lord Corlys? He should be here to receive the King.
欢迎来到高潮城 陛下
Welcome to High Tide, Your Grace.
这是什么意思 兰娜尔小姐？
What is the meaning of this, Lady Laena?
这就是瓦列利安家族迎接国王的方式吗？
Is this how House Velaryon greets its King?
兰娜尔·瓦列利安
科利斯与雷妮丝·坦格利安之女
我的父亲刚结束长途旅行回到家中
My father has but just returned from his long journey
他已赶去九航厅
and he has hastened to the Hall of Nine
兰尼诺·瓦列利安
科利斯与雷妮丝·坦格利安之子
在那里等待陛下的到来
to await Your Grace's arrival.
行了 我们走吧
Let's just get on with it.
一个外来的……
An outsider...
混在土著里
among the natives.
拉里斯大人
Lord Larys.
拉里斯·斯壮
“弯足” 莱昂诺的次子
锦葵
Malvales.
一种罕见的花
A rare bloom.
原产于布拉佛斯
Indigenous to Braavos.
按理说 它不可能在这里长得这么繁茂
By all rights, it shouldn't be thriving here.
大自然 如此不可思议
Nature, such mystery.
- 今天天气还不错 - 确实
-The weather has been lovely. -Indeed.
然而对这个国家来说却是黑暗的一天
And yet it is a dark day for the realm.
你父亲是个好人
Your father was a good man.
取代他位置的你父亲也很好
As is yours who took his place.
然而
Yet still,
你父亲离任的方式……
the manner of your father's departure...
让人觉得有些不公平
it feels something of an injustice.
关于他离任的事情你知道什么？
What do you know of the matter of his leaving?
一个从未被邀请发言的人
When one is never invited to speak,
会懂得……观察
one learns instead to... observe.
你或许需要一个盟友？
You're perhaps in need of an ally?
我是王后
I'm the Queen.
- 我不缺盟友 - 那是自然
-I have no shortage of allies. -Naturally.
比如说雷妮拉公主
Princess Rhaenyra, for example.
讲清楚你的目的 大人
State your purpose, my lord.
我确实好奇如今她是否还可以依赖
I did wonder if she could be relied upon
因为她身体有所不适
now that she is unwell.
不适？
Unwell?
我可什么都没听说
I haven't heard anything.
请原谅我 陛下 我可能搞错了
Begging your pardon, Your Grace, I may be mistaken.
在您父亲被革职的那晚
It's just that on the very same night your father was dismissed,
大学士给公主的房间里送去了一碗茶
the Grand Maester delivered a tea to the Princess's chambers.
- 一碗茶？ - 是的
-A tea? -Yes.
大学士自己安排的？
That the Grand Maester himself brought?
据我所知 是国王的命令
At the direction of the King, as I understand it.
我倒是希望她没有什么不适
I do hope she's not unwell.
雷妮拉陪国王坐船去潮头岛了
Rhaenyra sailed with the King to Driftmark
- 昨天黎明时分出发的 - 这可是个好消息
-yesterday at daybreak. -Oh what good news.
我一定搞错了
I must've been in error.
可松了口气
Oh, a relief.
瞧 我原以为梅罗斯亲自出马的话……
See, I thought for Mellos himself, well...
那她的病情一定很严重
her condition must be something very serious.
发现自己搞错了的感觉真好
What happiness it is to have been wrong.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
来 表姐
Come, cousin.
咱们去看看早餐都有什么
Let us discover what might be had for breakfast.
科利斯·瓦列利安
“海蛇”“潮汛之主” 潮头岛伯爵
陛下
Your Grace.
起身 科利斯大人
Rise, Lord Corlys.
欢迎
Be welcome.
给您拿把椅子？
May I offer you a chair?
雷妮丝·坦格利安
“无冕女王” 韦赛里斯的堂姐 科利斯的妻子
堂弟！
Cousin!
公主
Princess.
- 你还好吗？ - 非常好
-Are you well? -Very.
恭喜你 莱昂诺大人
I congratulate you, Lord Lyonel.
我想象不到还有谁比你更适合担任国王之手
I can think of no man more suited to be the Hand of the King.
感谢夸奖 科利斯大人
That is very kind of you to say, Lord Corlys.
陛下授予我这个职位是我的荣幸
His Grace has honored me with the post.
我对奥托爵士深表遗憾
Pity about Ser Otto.
尽管我大部分时间都在宏伟的红堡中度过
Despite spending most of my days amidst the grandeur of the Red Keep,
高潮城的厅堂总能让我印象深刻
the halls of High Tide never fail to impress.
您过奖了 陛下
You flatter me, Your Grace.
不过我的确希望我们能在更愉快的氛围下见面
Though I do wish we could meet under happier pretenses.
- 怎么说？ - 戴蒙的妻子
-How so? -Daemon's wife,
雷娅·罗伊斯夫人 过世了
the Lady Rhea Royce, has passed.
打猎事故
A hunting mishap.
她从马背上摔下来
She was thrown from her horse.
这一摔 把脖子和头骨都摔碎了
Her neck and skull both crushed in the fall.
让人惊讶的死法
A most surprising end.
雷娅夫人骑马和打猎的高超技术众人皆知
Lady Rhea's skill as both rider and hunter were well-known.
- 七神残忍 - 的确
-The gods are cruel. -Indeed.
雷娅夫人是个优秀的女人 也是我弟弟的良配
Lady Rhea was a fine woman and a good wife to my brother.
可惜她和戴蒙没有继承人
Sad thing that she and Daemon have no heirs to succeed her.
她有符石城的继承权
She stood to inherit Runestone.
我们来聊聊开心些的话题吧
Mayhaps we can turn toward happier pursuits.
- 不了 谢谢 - 您想说什么 陛下？
-No, thank you. -What did you have in mind, Your Grace?
我想撮合一段婚姻 你的儿子 兰尼诺爵士……
I wish to propose a marriage between your son, Ser Laenor...
与我的女儿及继承人 雷妮拉公主
and my daughter and heir, the Princess Rhaenyra.
我们两家早就应该血脉相连了
It's long past time our houses were united in blood.
作为古瓦雷利亚最后的支柱
The last pillars of Old Valyria.
这对我和我的家族都是巨大的荣幸 陛下
You honor both me and my house, Your Grace.
不过有一些细节我希望能确定
There are certain details I would wish clarified
在雷妮丝公主和我接受这最……
before the Princess Rhaenys and I could accept this most...
慷慨的提议前说清
generous proposal.
什么细节？
What details?
我们想要了解您如何处理继承人的事宜
We would like to know how the succession will be handled.
雷妮拉是我的继承人
Rhaenyra is my heir.
在我死后 我的王位和头衔会传给她
Upon my death, my throne and my titles will pass to her.
她与兰尼诺爵士的第一个孩子 无论男女
She and Ser Laenor's firstborn child, regardless of gender,
都会从她的手里接过王位
will inherit the Iron Throne from her.
我是否可以假设 按照维斯特洛的传统…
Can I presume that, in keeping with Westerosi tradition...
他们的孩子会冠以父亲的姓氏？
their children would take their father's name?
也就是姓瓦列利安？
That they would be born Velaryons?
科利斯伯爵
Surely, Lord Corlys,
难道你以为坦格利安王朝将在我女儿这代结束
you are not proposing the Targaryen dynasty end with my daughter
仅仅因为她是女人？
simply because she is a woman?
我只是想澄清细节 陛下
I only seek clarity, Your Grace.
- 要不还是拿把椅子吧？ - 我不…
-Might I have a chair brought in for you? -I do not--
不 我不需要椅子
No. I do not require a chair.
兰尼诺爵士和雷妮拉的孩子们一出生
Upon their birth, Ser Laenor and Rhaenyra's children
就会冠以父亲的姓氏 也就是瓦列利安…
shall take their father's name, Velaryon...
以维护我们的传统
in keeping with our traditions.
但是
However,
当他们的头生子登上铁王座之时
at such time when their firstborn ascends the Iron Throne,
无论男女 都会改为坦格利安
he or she will do so bearing the name Targaryen.
龙王家族在七大王国的统治将再延续一个世纪
Dragons will rule the Seven Kingdoms for the next hundred years,
正如之前那个世纪一样
just as they did the last.
非常公平的折中
This is an equitable compromise.
很好
Good.
如果没别的事 就到此为止
Now, if there's nothing further.
说实话 非得与谁成婚的话 我很高兴这个人是你
In truth, if it had to be someone, I'm glad it is you.
我明白 这场联姻不是出自你的真心
I know this union is not what you would choose.
我对你没有意见 表姐
I hold nothing against you, cousin.
不 我——
No, I--
宁愿……
rather...
我可不可以把这比喻成个人口味？
Dare I say it is a matter of taste?
比起烧鹅 我更喜欢烤鸭
I prefer roast duck to goose.
说不出为什么
I cannot say why.
其实不是因为没试过
It's not for a lack of trying.
有些人生来就是喜欢烧鹅
There are those who like goose very well.
对我个人口味而言 烧鹅有些油腻
I find it a bit greasy for my taste.
无论我们的父辈达成何种协议
I know that whatever agreement being struck up there
都不会改变你的口味
will not change your appetites,
我也如此
nor will it change mine.
那么 你有什么提议？
And what do you propose?
让我们为父辈及国家履行自己的责任
That we perform our duty to our fathers and to the realm
完事之后…
and when it's done...
我们可以依照各自的口味用餐
each of us dines as we see fit.
韦赛里斯已经上床休息了 船正准备起航
Viserys has taken to bed while his ship is readied.
也许我……
Perhaps I...
要得太多了？
overextended myself?
把他逼得太狠？
Pushed him too close to the edge?
我的堂弟选择了驶入这场风暴 夫君
My cousin chose to sail into this tempest, husband.
国王亲自前来 请求与兰尼诺的婚约
It was undignified of the King to drag himself here
这已有失尊严
and beg for Laenor's hand.
兰尼诺在哪儿？
Where is Laenor?
- 他和雷妮拉在海滩散步 - 很好
-He and Rhaenyra are walking the coast. -Good.
他们看上去……亲近吗？
Do they seem... familiar?
他们从小一起长大
They grew up together.
亲近不成问题
Familiarity is not at issue.
我敢肯定 兰尼诺已经被雷妮拉迷住了
I'm sure Laenor was already taken with her.
这几年 她是越来越漂亮了
She's grown quite comely these last few years.
你知道他的本性
You know his true nature.
他还年轻
He's still young.
会长大的
He will outgrow it.
这世上哪有什么乐子……
There is no pleasure in the world like...
比得了跟女人上床
bedding a woman.
这是把我们的儿子置于险境
We are placing our son in danger.
七大王国的领主们向雷妮拉屈膝下跪
The lords of the realm bent the knee to Rhaenyra
向她效忠
and swore obeisance to her.
那是在真正的王子出生之前
That was before there was a true-born prince
而他名叫伊耿·坦格利安
named Aegon Targaryen.
雷妮拉的继承权将会受到挑战
Rhaenyra's succession will be challenged.
她 她的丈夫 以及他们的孩子 必然要面临刀剑的威胁
Knives will come out for her, her husband, and for their heirs.
我们家族控制着全国的海军以及一半的龙
Our house controls the realm's navy and half its dragons.
谁若蠢到挑战雷妮拉的继承权
Anyone fool enough to challenge Rhaenyra's claim
- 只会被碾碎 - 为了什么 科利斯 财富？权力？
-will be crushed. -To what end, Corlys? Wealth? Power?
- 自尊？ - 公正
-Pride? -Justice.
不管按什么法理
By all rights,
都应该是你成为七大王国的女王
you should be Queen of the Seven Kingdoms.
抢走你王冠的人就是——
You were robbed of the crown by--
我从未戴上王冠 因为七大王国不会允许此事发生
I never wore the crown because the realm would not have it so.
我可以弥补这个
And I would remedy that
狭隘的错误 用上一切必要的手——
small-minded error by any means necessar--
我早就不想这事了 科利斯
I myself have put the business behind me, Corlys.
我一直不敢面对你不得不娶妻的那天
I've always feared the day you'd have to marry a woman.
现在 这天要来了
And now it comes.
你的未婚妻自愿允许你
Your betrothed gives you leave
乔佛里·隆莫斯
兰尼诺·瓦列利安的男伴
继续享用大餐
of her own free will to continue partaking of.
我是烤鸭还是烧鹅来着？
Was I the duck or the goose?
我过来直面命运 你却拿它开起了玩笑？
I've come to meet my fate and you make a jape of it?
听着 雷妮拉会成为七大王国的女王
Look, Rhaenyra will be Queen of the Seven Kingdoms
而你会是她的王夫
and you will be her king consort.
想想比武大会
Think of the tournament,
盛宴 还有海战吧
the feast, the battles at sea.
您今天会戴上王冠吗？陛下
Will you wear your crown today, Your Grace?
傻子
You're a fool.
你得有个贴身护卫
You will need a sworn protector.
这远比我们预想的要好
This is better than we could've hoped for.
她有自己的情人
She has a paramour of her own.
我好奇他是谁
I wonder who it is.
一大清早 你也睡不着吗？
Did sleep flee you as well this morning?
我要见您 公主殿下
I needed to see you, Princess.
坦白地说 我也是
I confess I had a similar desire.
我们相识的这些年里 您时不时向我吐露心声
You have confided in me now and then over the years of our acquaintance.
我猜 恕我冒昧 我多少……了解您一点
I feel, forgive me, that I, I know you... a bit.
你了解的可不止一点
You know more than a bit.
我总听您说 您有多么厌恶身居高位所要面对的命运
I've heard you say so many times how you loathe the lot of your position,
您反感父亲心血来潮的婚约指命
that you are to be married off at your father's whim
完全没考虑您内心的渴望
with no thought given to the yearning of your own heart,
然而 这一天还是来了
and now the day comes.
虽然兰尼诺爵士善良正直 但您……并没有选他
Ser Laenor is a good and, and decent man, but you, you did not choose him.
- 有人为您做了选择 - 你说的对
-He was chosen for you. -That's true.
倘若还有另一条路……
If there were another path...
能通往自由……
one that led to freedom...
您愿意走吗？
would you tread it?
雷妮拉 我来君临之前
Rhaenyra, before I came here,
是风暴地的骑士
I was a knight in the Stormlands.
我很了解阳戟城的港口
I have deep knowledge of the port at Sunspear
我曾在那儿见过厄斯索斯的商船扬帆起航
where I've seen the ships of Essos setting sail
满载橙子和肉桂而归
with their hulls full of oranges and cinnamon
我一直希望能看看那些船航向了哪里
and I've always wished to see where they went.
你想要告假吗？
Are you asking for leave?
我是想请求你跟我走……
I'm asking you to come with me...
远离这一切
away from all of this.
离开继承人身份带来的负担和侮辱
From the burdens and indignities of your inheritance.
让我们抛下这一切 一起去探索这个世界……
Let us leave it all behind and see the world together...
我们可以隐姓埋名
where we'll be nameless,
自由自在……
and free...
去任何我们想去的地方 无所顾忌地相爱
free to go where we like, to love as we like.
在厄斯索斯……
In Essos...
你可以嫁给我
you could marry me.
为了爱情而结婚
A marriage for love,
而不是为了王位
not for the crown.
我就是王 克里斯顿爵士
I am the crown, Ser Criston.
或者说我会成王
Or I will be.
我可能会厌烦职责
I may chafe at my duties,
但你以为我会选择身败名裂
but do you think I would choose infamy
就为了一筐橙子或是一张航向亚夏的船票吗？
in exchange for a bushel of oranges or a ship to Asshai?
我的责任就是
It is my duty
与一位豪门贵族结婚
to marry a nobleman from a great house
兰尼诺爵士会是一个好丈夫
and Ser Laenor will make a fine husband.
但是我的……
But my...
我的婚姻……
my marriage...
并不意味着我们关系的终结
does not have to be the end.
克里斯顿爵士 兰尼诺和我达成了共识
Ser Criston, Laenor and I have an understanding.
我允许他去追求自己的兴趣……
I've granted him leave to pursue his own interests...
作为回报 他也给予我同样的自由
and in turn, he's granted me the same.
所以你想要我当你的婊子？
So you want me to be your whore?
我想要我们像一开始那样
I want us to continue as we began,
你是我的贴身护卫 我的白骑士
with you as my sworn protector, my white knight.
我立过誓的
I took an oath.
作为御林铁卫的骑士
As a, as a knight of, of your Kingsguard.
我曾发誓守贞 我打破了这个誓言
An oath of chastity. I've broken it.
- 我不会告诉任何人—— - 我 我玷污了我的 我的白——我的白袍
-I won't tell anyone-- -I've, I've soiled my, my, wh-- my white cloak.
这是我他妈名下唯一的东西
And it's the only thing I have to my fucking name!
我以为如果我们结婚了 也许我能挽回荣誉
I thought if we were married, I might be able to restore it.
铁王座比我更重要
The Iron Throne looms larger than me,
比我家族中任何人都更重要
larger than anyone in my family.
征服者伊耿统一了七国
Aegon the Conqueror united the Seven Kingdoms
让它走上了一条——
and put them on a path--
克里斯顿爵士
Ser Criston.
- 去找学士 - 退后
-Fetch the Maester! -Get back.
去找梅罗斯！退后！
Get Mellos! Get back!
准备坩埚
Prepare the crucible.
去找水蛭
We'll need leeches.
克里斯顿爵士……
Ser Criston...
您被传唤了
you've been summoned.
我刚刚才离开公主
I left the Princess just minutes ago.
不是公主 爵士
Not the Princess, ser.
是王后
The Queen.
克里斯顿爵士来了 陛下
Ser Criston, Your Grace.
退下吧
That will be all.
恐怕我得问你一件 一件敏感的事情 克里斯顿爵士
I fear I must question you on a, on a delicate matter, Ser Criston.
我一贯是您的仆人 王后
I am your servant as always, my Queen.
这关系到我们亲爱的公主雷妮拉
It concerns our dear Princess Rhaenyra.
请坐
Please.
你是她的贴身护卫 自然是对她忠诚的
You are her sworn protector and rightly loyal to her.
是的
I am.
戴蒙回来的那晚……
The night of Daemon's return...
有一个传言……
there's been a rumor...
或者说 我父亲收到了一份……
or rather, my father received an accounting of...
某人行为失当的报告
a lapse of morals
也许是发生在——
that may have occurred between--
当然 我觉得质疑公主的德行是不可思议的
It is, of course, unthinkable for me to question the virtue of the Princess,
我一向十分敬重公主
whom I hold in highest regard,
但我——我确实想过 如果……
but I-I, I did, however, wonder if...
我不是不知道在年轻的冲动下……
I'm not unaware that in flush of youth...
也许会犯下一些错误……
there may be errors made...
决定违背……
breaches in resolve,
违背 或者说疏忽——
breaches, or rather lapses--
确有此事 陛下
It happened, Your Grace.
您所暗示的罪行
The sin you allude to.
是我犯的
I have committed it.
确实是在她的挑逗下 但是那不应该——
At her instigation, it is true, but that should--
我没有借口
It is no excuse.
我背了誓
My oath has been broken.
我使自己蒙羞
I have dishonored myself.
我不值得体谅
I deserve no consideration.
但如果……
But if...
作为一位仁慈的王后 若您有意怜悯……
as a clement Queen, you are inclined to pity...
我只请求……
I would ask only this...
与其阉割我
that rather than gelding me
折磨我
and having me tortured
不如仁慈地判决我死刑
you would sentence me mercifully to death.
感谢你的坦诚 克里斯顿爵士
Thank you for your honesty, Ser Criston.
你可以走了
You may go.
休息一下吧 陛下 我会拿水蛭来
Rest now, Your Grace. I will bring the leeches.
恕我冒昧 大学士
If I may, Grand Maester,
我自作主张准备了一副新的
I took the liberty of preparing a fresh set
也许会更有效的草药膏
of herbal poultices that might be more effective.
不需要 欧维尔
That will not be necessary, Orwyle.
水蛭一向能使陛下放松
The leechings have always brought His Grace relief.
梅罗斯
大学士
这个能帮他入睡
To help him sleep.
王后呢？
Where's the Queen?
据我所知她另有他事 陛下
I was given to understand that she is otherwise occupied, Your Grace.
我会作为一个好国王流芳百世吗 莱昂诺？
Will I be remembered as a good king, Lyonel?
陛下？
Your Grace?
史书里会怎样评价我呢？
What will they say of me when the histories are written?
我既没有战斗过 也没有征服过
I have neither fought nor conquered,
也没有遭受过重大的失败
nor suffered any great defeat.
有些人会说这是福气
Some might call that good fortune.
这可不好写歌谣啊 是不是？
It hardly makes a good song, does it?
能在一百年 五百年后的宴会上
To be sung at feasts in a hundred years...
唱起的歌谣
five hundred.
您继承了杰赫里斯国王的遗志
You have carried King Jaehaerys's legacy.
维持王国长盛不衰
And kept the realm strong.
生活在和平当中
Is it not better to live in peace
不比死后有歌谣传颂更好吗？
than to have songs sung after you are dead?
或许吧
Perhaps.
但我有点渴望经历考验
But there is a part of me wishes I'd been tested.
我总觉得在坩埚之中
I often think that in the crucible,
我也许会被铸造成一个不同的人
I may have been forged a different man.
很多遭受考验的人 只希望能免于此难
Many that are tested, only wish to have been spared it.
要是换个人 说不定会向我保证
Another lord might assure me that I would rise like
假以时机我可以像征服者伊耿一样雄起
Aegon the Conqueror given the chance.
- 陛下 这是—— - 你是对的
-Your Grace, that is-- -You're right.
你总是对的
You're right as always.
也许 最好还是别知道答案了
It is perhaps best not to know.
梅丽亚斯
雷妮丝的龙
海烟
兰尼诺的龙
怀着极其喜悦的心情
It is with great pleasure
韦赛里斯国王陛下宣布
that His Grace, King Viserys, announces the start
王家婚礼庆典正式开始
of the royal wedding celebrations.
兰尼斯特家族及其领主 杰森·兰尼斯特
House Lannister with their lord, Jason Lannister.
哈罗德·维斯特林
御林铁卫队长
西境总督 凯岩城之主
Lord Paramount of the West, and Master of Casterly Rock.
杰森·兰尼斯特
凯岩城公爵
泰兰·兰尼斯特
杰森的双胞胎弟弟 海政大臣
海塔尔家族及其领主 霍巴特·海塔尔
House Hightower with their lord, Hobert Hightower.
南境之灯塔 学城的守护者
Beacon of the South, Defender of the Citadel,
霍巴特·海塔尔
南境灯塔 学城守护者 旧镇之音 奥托的哥哥
旧镇之音……
the Voice of Oldtown...
恭喜 陛下
Congratulations, Your Grace.
您为公主找到了佳偶
You have made a fine match for the Princess.
谢谢你 杰森公爵
Thank you, Lord Jason.
我想不到比兰尼诺爵士更好的人选了
I could think of no better man than Ser Laenor.
如果接风宴就已经这样了
Well, if this is only the welcome feast,
得承认 我想不出您为婚礼准备了什么
I admit, I cannot imagine what you might have planned for the wedding.
我女儿是未来的女王
My daughter is the future queen.
我希望这场婚礼是史无前例的
I wanted this to be a wedding for the histories.
王后在哪里呢？
Where is the Queen?
我想要致以敬意
I had hoped to pay my respects.
我听说王后仍然在为出席庆典做准备
I understand the Queen is still readying herself for the celebrations.
这就是男人才能开战的原因
This is why men wage war
女人永远不会及时做好战斗准备
because women would never be ready for the battle in time.
你的到来总是那么令人愉悦 杰森公爵
Your presence is always such a pleasure, Lord Jason.
公主 陛下 告退
Princess, Your Grace.
陛下 雷妮拉公主 恭喜
Your Grace, Princess Rhaenyra, congratulations are in order.
我们非常荣幸你来做客 杰洛爵士
We are very honored to have you as a guest, Ser Gerold.
不得不说
I must say, I was most distressed
雷娅夫人不幸去世的消息让我非常悲痛
to hear of the Lady Rhea's tragic passing.
请你节哀顺变
I'm very sorry for your loss.
雷娅夫人是位独特的人
Lady Rhea was a unique character.
我们将难得再见如此之人
Her kind is not soon to be seen again.
如果王室有什么能帮助罗伊斯家族的——
If there is anything the crown might do to aid House Royce--
瓦列利安家族的科利斯伯爵
Lord Corlys of House Velaryon.
潮汛之主 潮头岛之主
Lord of the Tides, Master of Driftmark.
和他的夫人 雷妮丝·坦格利安公主
And his lady wife, Princess Rhaenys Targaryen.
以及他们的儿子兼继承人 兰尼诺·瓦列利安爵士
And their son and heir, Ser Laenor Velaryon,
未来的王夫
the future king consort.
林曼·毕斯柏里
财政大臣
-我的未婚夫 -我的未婚妻
-My Betrothed. -My Betrothed.
欢迎各位莅临庆典
Be welcome, as we join together in celebration.
今夜只是开始
Tonight is only its beginning.
让我们向王室最古老
We honor the crown's oldest
也是最有力的盟友瓦列利安家族致敬
and fiercest ally, House Velaryon.
他们可追溯到古瓦雷利亚和巨龙纪元
Reaching back to the days of Old Valyria and the Age of Dragons.
在坦格利安家族和……
With House Targaryen and--
哈尔温·斯壮
“碎骨人” 莱昂诺的长子
国王肯定不高兴了
The King will not be happy.
话说一半被打断
Right in the midst of his speech.
当旧镇召集封臣开战时
The beacon on the Hightower,
你知道参天塔的灯火是什么颜色吗？
do you know what color it glows when Oldtown calls its banners to war?
绿色
Green.
恭喜 我的继女
Congratulations, stepdaughter.
这真是你的好福气
What a blessing this is for you.
请就座
Please be seated.
说到哪了？
Where was I?
两大家族的结合 陛下
The joining of the two houses, Your Grace.
没错
Yeah.
是的
Yes.
坦格利安家族和瓦列利安家族即将联合
With House Targaryen and House Velaryon united,
我希望这昭示着维斯特洛的第二个巨龙纪元
I hope to herald in a second Age of Dragons in Westeros.
在今夜的小场面之后……
And after tonight's small affair...
会有七天的比武和盛宴
seven days of tournament and feasting.
最后……
At the end of it all...
最后是……王室婚礼……
At the end of it all, a royal wedding...
缔结了我的爱女
between my daughter,
我的继承人
my heir...
你们未来的女王
your future Queen...
与潮头岛继承人 兰尼诺·瓦列利安爵士
and Ser Laenor Velaryon, the heir to Driftmark.
我一向不擅长跳舞
I was never much of a dancer.
这和打架没什么区别
It's not much different to combat.
我希望结果会有所不同
I shall hope for a different outcome.
- 陛下 - 伯伯 感谢光临
-Your Grace. -We thank you for coming, uncle.
我原本担心你离开父亲的庇护
I worried that given leave of your father's shadow,
会在君临的烈日下枯萎
you might wither in King's Landing's sun.
但你身姿傲然
But you stood tall.
记住 旧镇与你同在
Know that Oldtown stands with you.
在谷地 人们必须为自己的罪行负责
In the Vale, men are made to answer for their crimes.
甚至坦格利安族人也不例外
Even Targaryens.
你是谁？
Who are you?
符石城的杰洛·罗伊斯爵士
Ser Gerold Royce of Runestone.
然后呢？
And?
我是你已故夫人的堂兄
I am cousin to your late lady wife.
没错 真可怕
Yes. Terrible thing.
我极度悲伤 多么悲惨的意外
I'm positively bereft. Such a tragic accident.
你比任何人都清楚 这不是意外
You know better than anyone, it was no accident.
你是来认罪的吗 杰洛爵士？
Are you confessing some guilt, Ser Gerold?
我是控诉的
I am making an accusation.
在君临 人们必须为自己的诽谤负责
In King's Landing, men are made to answer for their slanders.
甚至你这样的老青铜婊子也不例外
Even old bronze cunts like you.
事实上 我很高兴你能来
The truth is, I'm glad you've come.
我想和你谈谈我的继承问题
I wish to speak to you about my inheritance.
- 什么继承问题？ - 雷娅夫人和我没有子嗣
-What inheritance? -Lady Rhea and I had no heirs.
作为她的丈夫 她的一切权利现在都传承给我了
As her husband, whatever she was due now passes to me.
她将继承符石城的一切 对吧？
She stood to inherit all of Runestone. Did she not?
我侄女完婚后 我会飞到鹰巢城
After my niece's wedding, I plan to fly to the Eyrie
亲自向简妮夫人请愿
and petition Lady Jeyne myself.
或许我们能在那里再碰面 杰洛爵士
Perhaps I'll see you there, Ser Gerold.
有人告诉过你 你几乎和你哥哥一样漂亮吗？
Has anybody ever told you you're nearly as pretty as your brother?
你过誉了 王子
You flatter me, my Prince.
- 听说你夫人的事我很难过 - 不用难过 我不伤心
-I was sorry to hear about your lady wife. -Don't be, I wasn't.
我的夫人对我从来都不是很好
My lady was never very kind to me.
我知道是谁了
I know who it is.
那个英俊的情人
The handsome paramour.
谁？
Who?
克里斯顿·科尔爵士
Ser Criston Cole.
她的贴身护卫？
Her sworn protector?
看看他
Look at him.
被迷得神魂颠倒
The man is fully cunt-struck.
坦格利安王子 勇猛的骑士和驭龙者
A Targaryen prince, a dashing knight, and a dragonrider.
你似乎是每个少女的梦想
You appear to be every young maiden's dream.
那只是因为你还不了解我
That's only because you don't know me yet.
我相信克里斯顿爵士的白袍上
I believe Ser Criston has bloodied that white cloak of his
沾染了你新娘的处子血
with your bride's maidenhead.
小点声
Keep your voice down.
也许我们可以为此补救 王子
Perhaps that is something we might remedy, my Prince.
也许吧
Perhaps it is.
这是件好事 她知道你的秘密
This is a good thing. She knows your secret,
现在你也知道她的
and now you know hers.
嘿！
Hey!
他们真是天造地设的一对 是吧？
They make a handsome match, don't they?
什么？
What?
公主和兰尼诺爵士
The Princess and Ser Laenor.
嘿！
Hey!
在下乔佛里·隆莫斯爵士
Ser Joffrey Lonmouth,
人称“热吻骑士”
or the Knight of Kisses, they call me,
虽然我也不知道为什么这么叫我
though I don't know why.
我在值守 有何贵干？
I'm on watch. What's your business?
你不认识我 克里斯顿爵士
You don't know me, Ser Criston.
但我们都深深纠缠在这场联姻中
But we are both deeply invested in this union.
嘿！
Hey!
乔佛里爵士 如果你有话不妨直说
If you have something to say, Ser Joffrey, speak it.
兰尼诺爵士是我的心上人
Ser Laenor is quite dear to me.
我知道公主对你来说也一样
As I know the Princess is to you.
我们应该互相发誓保护他们
We should swear to each other to guard them,
和他们的秘密 如果他们安全……
and their secrets, because if those are kept safe...
我们也会平安无恙
then so are we all.
嘿！
Hey!
哈尔温爵士 我可以借你的舞伴吗？
May I, Ser Harwin?
当然可以 王子
Of course, my Prince.
嘿！
Hey!
这就是你想要的吗？
我都不知道你会在意我想要什么
这不适合你
兰尼诺是个好人 好骑士
他会让你厌烦无聊的
婚姻只是一场政治安排 我听过这句话
我的婚姻最近结束了
那就带我走
这不是你一直以来的目的吗？
我还没结婚 但时间正在飞逝
你肯定有武器
从我父亲的御林铁卫中杀出一条路
带我去龙石岛让我成为你的妻子
嘿！
Hey!
七层地狱啊 到底发生了什么？
What in the Seven Hells is going on?
兰尼诺！
Laenor!
停下！
Stop this!
雷妮拉在哪里？
Where's Rhaenyra?
公主？
Princess?
放我下来！
Put me down!
七神之爱神圣永恒
The love of the Seven is holy and eternal.
生命和爱的源泉
The source of life and love.
今夜我们一同站在这里感恩赞美
We stand here tonight in thanks and praise
两个灵魂合二为一
to join two souls as one.
天父……
Father...
圣母……
Mother...
战士……
Warrior...
铁匠……
Smith...
少女……
Maiden...
老妪……
Crone...
陌客
Stranger.
现在请听他们的誓言
Hear now their vows.
我属于你 你属于我
I am yours and you are mine.
无论何至 此诺恒一
Whatever may come.
我属于你 你属于我
I am yours and you are mine.
无论何至 此诺恒一
Whatever may come.
于此 在诸神和世人见证下
Here, in the presence of gods and men,
我宣布……
I proclaim...
瓦列利安家族的兰尼诺
Laenor of House Velaryon
和坦格利安家族的雷妮拉
Rhaenyra of House Targaryen,
结为夫妇
to be man and wife.
一个躯体……
One flesh...
一个心灵……
one heart...
一个魂魄……
one soul...
永恒不变
now and forever.
克里斯顿爵士
Ser Criston.